Guide to the Democratic Socialists of America Records TAM.105
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Democratic Socialists of America Records
1940-2023, ongoing
1972-2006
Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archives
Democratic Socialists of America
Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (U.S.)
TAM.105
164.7 Linear Feet in 140 record cartons, 16 manuscript boxes, 4 half manuscript boxes, 4 media boxes, 4 small flat boxes, 1 oversized flat box, 2 audio reels in oversized shared manuscript box, 1 folder in oversized shared flat box, and born digital items in 1 shared media box
195.26 Gigabytes
43 websites in 43 archived websites.
87 videocassettes (vhs)
146 audiocassettes
7 videocassettes (hi8)
6 videocassettes (u-matic)
40 sound tape reels
Democratic Socialists of America (DSA) was founded in 1982 with the merger of the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) and the New American Movement (NAM). DSOC was led by Michael Harrington (1928-1989), the author of The Other America (1962). NAM grew out of the New Left and feminist movements. The Democratic Socialists of America is the largest socialist organization in the United States, with over 92,000 members, chapters in all 50 states (both statistics as of 2022), and a youth and student section, Young Democratic Socialists of America. The Democratic Socialists of America Records consist of materials created by the organization, its leaders, and its members from its inception to its current state. These materials include publications; national board and committee meeting minutes and agendas; local chapter meeting minutes; conference programs; member correspondence and mailings; reports and proceedings of the Socialist International, of which DSA is the U.S. affiliate; files on the DSA-founded Institute for Democratic Socialism; and files on other labor and left organizations, as well as websites created by the DSA. The collection also contains published and unpublished writings of Michael Harrington.
Conditions Governing Access
Materials are open without restrictions.
Accruals
Additional accruals are expected.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Materials were donated by the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee in 1980. Additional accessions were donated by the Democratic Socialists of America in 1983-1985, 1989, and 2019-2023. The accession numbers associated with these gifts are 1970-018, 1980-017, 2019-017, 2019-051, 2019-088, 2019-147, 2019-128, 2020-014, 2020-018, 2021-006, 2021-001, 2021-017, 2021-044, 2021-042, 2021-069, 2021-062, 2021-080, 2021-087, 2022-031, 2022-039, 2022-050, 2022-064, 2022-066, 2022-072, 2022-092, 2023-025, NPA-2001-088, NPA-2005-191, NPA-2002-022, NPA-2006-030, and NPA-2005-128.
http://www.dsausa.org/, http://theactivist.org/, http://www.ydsusa.org/, and https://talkingunion.wordpress.com/ were initially selected by curators and captured through the use of The California Digital Library's Web Archiving Service in 2008-2009 as part of the Communism, Socialism, Trotskyism Web Archive. https://fund-dsausa.nationbuilder.com/ was added in 2013. In 2015, this website was migrated to Archive-It. Archive-It uses web crawling technology to capture websites at a scheduled time and displays only an archived copy, from the resulting WARC file, of the website. In 2018, https://y.dsausa.org/, https://dsa.actionkit.com/donate/dsa-fund/, https://electoral.dsausa.org/, https://ecosocialists.dsausa.org/, https://democraticleft.dsausa.org/, https://teachers.dsausa.org/, and https://store.dsausa.org/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites are 2019.088. In April-May 2019, https://labor.dsausa.org/, https://fund.dsausa.org/, https://socialistforum.dsausa.org/, and https://international.dsausa.org/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites are 2019.128. In October 2019, https://dsaantiwar.com/, https://tech.dsausa.org/, https://breadandrosesdsa.org/, https://medicareforall.dsausa.org/, http://closethecampsoct.org/, and https://bernie.dsausa.org/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2019.147. In December 2019, https://www.religioussocialism.org/ and https://socialistcall.com/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites are 2020.014. http://feeds.feedburner.com/religioussocialismpodcast/ and https://blubrry.com/thecallradio/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites are 2020.018. In 2020, 96 DSA related Google Documents and Sheets were added to Archive-it to better capture these materials directly. The accession numbers associated with these websites are 2021.006, 2021.011, 2021.017, 2021.042, and 2021.044. In January 2021, https://workerorganizing.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2021.062. In February 2021, additional Google documents and https://design.dsausa.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2021.069. In March 2021, https://powerfortexas.org/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2021.080. In May 2021, https://pro-act.dsausa.org/ and https://www.youtube.com/channel/UCp2lDGhpmtJdBRIwznXH0vQ/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2021.087. In November 2021, https://greennewschools.com/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2022.031. In December 2021, https://drive.google.com/drive/u/0/folders/1z87YDk3DGkPJF59atZdiDoOgtVp8xc2Q/ was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2022.039. In March 2022, https://laborsolidarity.com/ and https://www.youtube.com/DemocraticSocialistsofAmericaDSA/videos was added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2022.050. In June 2022, https://docs.google.com/document/d/e/2PACX-1vSZU995aYZamOReQJBIyrgTiifoAzg950aBGnJ4u7MCFryuY6v7ud5e_WsOH_oftLOu6ilmfi-UWTDD/pub was added. The accession number associated with this website is 2022.064. In July 2022, https://protectabortion.org/ and https://www.dishrag.org/. The accession number associated with these websites is 2022.066. In August 2022, https://palestine.dsausa.org/ and https://education.dsausa.org/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2022.072. In November 2022, https://cam4a.org/, https://rfs.dsausa.org/, https://dsaic.org/, and https://convention2021.dsausa.org/ were added. The accession number associated with these websites is 2022.092. In February 2023, https://www.greennewslate.com/ and https://convention2023.dsausa.org/. The accession number associated with these websites is 2023.025.
Take Down Policy
Archived websites are made accessible for purposes of education and research. NYU Libraries have given attribution to rights holders when possible; however, due to the nature of archival collections, we are not always able to identify this information.
If you hold the rights to materials in our archived websites that are unattributed, please let us know so that we may maintain accurate information about these materials.
If you are a rights holder and are concerned that you have found material on this website for which you have not granted permission (or is not covered by a copyright exception under US copyright laws), you may request the removal of the material from our site by submitting a notice, with the elements described below, to the repository email.
Please include the following in your notice: Identification of the material that you believe to be infringing and information sufficient to permit us to locate the material; your contact information, such as an address, telephone number, and email address; a statement that you are the owner, or authorized to act on behalf of the owner, of an exclusive right that is allegedly infringed and that you have a good-faith belief that use of the material in the manner complained of is not authorized by the copyright owner, its agent, or the law; a statement that the information in the notification is accurate and made under penalty of perjury; and your physical or electronic signature. Upon receiving a notice that includes the details listed above, we will remove the allegedly infringing material from public view while we assess the issues identified in your notice.
Arrangement
The records have been arranged into 14 series; the series arrangement is as follows:
Series I. Organizational History
Series II. Governing Bodies
Series III. Committees and Commissions
Series IV. Youth Section/Young Democratic Socialists of America
Series V. Staff and Administrative Materials
Series VI. Conventions
Series VII. Publications
Series VIII. Chapters
Series IX. Events and Publicity
Series X. Membership and Fundraising
Series XI. Socialist International
Series XII. Institute for Democratic Socialism/Democratic Socialists of America Fund
Series XIII. Subject Files
Series XIV. Archived Websites
All of the series are arranged chronologically, with the exception of Series XIII, which is arranged alphabetically.
Historical Note
Democratic Socialists of America (DSA) was founded in 1982 with the merger of the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) and the New American Movement (NAM). DSOC was led by Michael Harrington (1928-1989), the author of The Other America (1962). NAM grew out of the New Left and feminist movements. Harrington and others, including Carl Shier, left the Socialist Party, USA (later known as the Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, USA, or SP-DSF) over its support of the Vietnam War, and became the principal founders of DSOC. In its early days, DSA established chapters in virtually every state, including chapters at many colleges and universities; worked to build a progressive presence in the Democratic Party through its Democratic Agenda project; collaborated closely with progressive labor unions and leaders, feminists, and others to promote a social democratic agenda and a peaceful foreign policy; and advocated for socialism while strongly criticizing Communism. DSA also published Democratic Left, founded the Socialist Scholars Conference (now known as the Left Forum), and established the Insitute for Democratic Socialism. DSA is the largest socialist organization in the United States, with over 92,000 members, chapters in all 50 states (both statistics as of 2022), and a youth and student section (Young Democratic Socialists of America). It serves as the U.S. affiliate of Socialist International. The organization is committed to the idea that "working people should run both the economy and society democratically to meet human needs, not to make profits for a few."
Sources Cited:
Democratic Socialists of America. "History." Accessed June 14, 2023. https://www.dsausa.org/about-us/history/.
Democratic Socialists of America. "Leadership and Structure." Accessed June 14, 2023. https://www.dsausa.org/about-us/structure/.
The Democratic Socialists of America Fund. "History." Accessed June 14, 2023. https://fund.dsausa.org/history/.
Young Democratic Socialists of America. "Home." Accessed June 14, 2023. https://y.dsausa.org/.
Custodial History
Democratic Socialists of America Audiocassette Collection (OH 058), previously a discrete collection, was incorporated into TAM 105 in June 2023.
Audiovisual Access Policies and Procedures
Audiovisual materials have not been preserved and may not be available to researchers. Materials not yet digitized will need to have access copies made before they can be used. To request an access copy, or if you are unsure if an item has been digitized, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596, with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Born-Digital Access Policies and Procedures
Advance notice is required for the use of computer records. Original physical digital media is restricted. Born-digital materials have not been transferred and may not be available to researchers. Researchers may request access copies. To request that material be transferred, or if you are unsure if material has been transferred, please contact Tamiment Library and Robert F. Wagner Labor Archive, special.collections@nyu.edu, 212-998-2596, with the collection name, collection number, and a description of the item(s) requested. A staff member will respond to you with further information.
Related Archival Materials
New American Movement Records (TAM 051)
Michael Harrington Papers (TAM 209)
Maurice Isserman Research Files for The Other American: The Life of Michael Harrington (TAM 239)
Scope and Contents
The Democratic Socialists of America Records consist of materials created by the organization, its leaders, and its members from its inception to its current state. These materials reflect the organization's efforts to fight for reforms that empower working people through a variety of tactics, including legislative reform and direct action. Materials include Michael Harrington's early writing (both published and unpublished), which reflects positions later adopted by DSA; correspondence, memos, publications, resolutions, and mailings from Harrington's term as the chair of the Socialist Party, USA; letters documenting his resignation as chair and subsequent resignation from the party; and meeting minutes and correspondence of the Coalition Caucus, the predecessor of DSOC. Materials also include publications, correspondence, and meeting minutes from DSOC and the New American Movement (NAM) before they merged; also included are materials documenting the merger. Other materials consist of minutes, agendas, statements, and reports from DSA's governing bodies (National Board, National Executive Committee, and National Political Committee) and minutes, reports, statements, and publications from its various committees, commissions, and caucuses (including the Feminist Commission, Religious Socialism Committee, and the Democratic Agenda, among others). There is a large amount of material from the Young Democratic Socialists of America (YDSA), which began as the Youth Section; included are convention proceedings, mailings, chapter reports, and executive committee minutes. On the national level, there are materials from the office (staff meeting minutes and correspondence); convention programs, papers, and speeches; events and projects (such as Justice for All and Center for Democratic Values, among others); publications (Democratic Left, Socialist Forum, and position papers); clippings and articles about DSA; membership mailings; and fundraising campaigns and grant applications. On the regional and local level, there are chapter meeting minutes, reports, and local convention programs. Additionally, there are meeting minutes, resolutions, and conference proceedings from Socialist International, and financial records, correspondence, and conference programs from the Institute for Democratic Socialism. DSA often worked with other organizations and unions with similar interests, like the National Organization for Women and Amalgamated Clothing and Textile Workers Union; included are printed matter from these organizations (brochures and newsletters) and conference materials. The websites of the national organization, chapter organizations, committees, YDSA, and other offshoots are also included in this collection. This collection also includes audio and video recordings of convention sessions, lectures, and television appearances by DSA leaders on analog and electronic formats. Additional born-digital materials contain mailings, printed matter (brochures, flyers, and conference programs), and position papers, mostly from the early 1990s-2010s.
Correspondence.; Labor unions and socialism -- United States.; Circular letters.; College students -- Political activity -- United States.; Manuscripts; Manuscripts for publication.; Lectures.; Mailing lists.; Socialism -- United States -- History.; Socialism -- United States -- Periodicals.; Speeches.; Socialism -- United States.; Proceedings.; Audiocassettes.; Socialism and youth -- United States.; Reports.; Women and socialism -- United States.; Surveys (documents).; Videocassettes.; Poverty -- United States.; Newsletters.; New Left -- United States.; Minutes (administrative records); Web sites.; Food industry and trade -- Employees -- Labor unions; Reproductive rights -- United States; Capitalism.; Shier, Carl; Socialist International (1951- ); Socialist Party-Social Democratic Federation; Institute for Democratic Socialism (U.S.); New American Movement (Organization); Democratic Socialists of America. Feminist Commission; Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee. Youth Section; Harrington, Michael, 1928-1989; Democratic Party (U.S.); Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (U.S.); Democratic Socialists of America. Democratic Agenda; Democratic National Convention (1980) (New York, N.Y); Democratic National Convention (1976) (New York, N.Y); Clark, Jack, 1949-; Democratic Socialists of America; Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (U.S.); Young Democratic Socialists.; Starbucks Workers Union
- Series I. Organizational History, 1959-1983; 1.75 Linear Feet in 4 manuscript boxes; 1 sound tape reels
  Scope and Contents
  This series chronicles the events leading to the founding of DSA. It documents Michael Harrington's early years with the Young People's Socialist League and his later role as chair of the Socialist Party, USA (which changed its name to Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, USA, or SP-DSF, around April 1972), through his resignation from the party and the formation of the Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) in 1973. Additionally, materials cover the early negotiations between DSOC and New American Movement (NAM), their eventual merger, and the formation of the Democratic Socialists of America (1983) through notes, resolutions, meeting minutes, negotiating instructions, and the merger agreement. Materials also include notes and meeting minutes from the Coalition Caucus, the precursor to DSOC; correspondence (most of which is from Michael Harrington and Carl Shier, Regional Director of the United Auto Workers and co-founder of DSOC with Harrington); Socialist Party, USA/SP-DSF mailings, resolutions, publications (such as New America), press releases, and Harrington's resignation letter; correspondence, memos, a proposed constitution, and the publication Socialist Reporter (a special report on the founding of DSOC) from the early days of DSOC; and early versions of DSA's constitution and bylaws. Michael Harrington's early published and unpublished writing is included here since it reflects the directions and views eventually adopted by DSOC. Published writing includes American Power in the Twentieth Century (published by the League for Industrial Democracy, 1967), and various articles for The New York Times and New York Herald Tribune, among others. Uunpublished writing includes a speech on youth and the labor movement, delivered at the 22nd Annual Central Labor Union Conference at the University of Illinois (December 1971), and an article draft on Vietnam (August 1971).
  - Notes on the History of Democratic Socialists of America, undated (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Harrington, Michael -- Young People's Socialist League, USA, 1959 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Harrington, Michael -- Published Writing, 1965-1973 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Harrington, Michael -- Unpublished Writing, 1971-1972 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Socialist Party, USA, 1970 (Box 1, Folder 5, Box 76, Quarter inch audio reel 105_0001-105_0002)
  - Socialist Party, USA, January-August 1971 (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Socialist Party, USA, September-December 1971 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Socialist Party, USA, circa 1971 (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Socialist Party, USA, January 1972 (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Socialist Party, USA, February 1972 (Box 2, Folder 1)
  - Socialist Party, USA/Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, USA, March-April 1972 (Box 2, Folder 2)
  - Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, USA, May-June 1972 (Box 2, Folder 3)
  - Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, USA, July-August 1972 (Box 2, Folder 4)
  - Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, USA -- Resignation of Michael Harrington as Chair, September-October 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, USA, November 1972 (Box 2, Folder 5)
  - Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, USA, December 1972 (Box 2, Folder 7)
  - Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, USA, circa 1972 (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Socialist Party-Democratic Socialist Federation, USA/Social Democrats, USA, 1973 (Box 2, Folder 9)
  - Coalition Caucus, January-March 1973 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC), April-May 1973 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) -- Resignation of Michael Harrington from Socialist Party, USA, June-July 1973 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) -- Proposed Constitution, August 1973 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC), September 1973 (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) -- Founding Convention, October 1973 (Box 3, Folder 6)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC), November-December 1973 (Box 3, Folder 7)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC), circa 1973 (Box 3, Folder 8)
  - Other Organizations -- Constitutions and Reports, 1972-1973 (Box 3, Folder 9)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) and New American Movement (NAM) -- Early Communication, 1974-1978 (Box 3, Folder 10)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) and New American Movement (NAM) -- Meetings and Negotiations, 1979-1980 (Box 3, Folder 11)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) and New American Movement (NAM) -- Negotiations, January-August 1981 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) and New American Movement (NAM) -- Negotiations, September-December 1981 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - Democratic Socialist Organizing Committee (DSOC) and New American Movement (NAM) -- Merger Convention and Unity Celebration, 1982 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - Democratic Socialists of America (DSA) -- Constitution and Bylaws, 1983 (Box 4, Folder 4)
- Series II. Governing Bodies, 1984-1992; 2.02 Linear Feet in 2 flat boxes and 1 manuscript box; 9 audiocassettes; 1 videocassettes (vhs)
  This series contains materials related to the governing bodies of DSA, from its time as DSOC. These materials include meeting minutes and agendas, correspondence and memos, reports, and notes from the National Board and the National Executive Committee (NEC). From circa 1978-early 1990s, there was also a National Office Committee (NOC), which focused on financial matters and events, such as the Convention. The minutes, reports, and memos of the NOC also are included here. This series also consists of National Political Committee (NPC) materials, which later took over the role of the board of directors; members are elected every two years by the delegates to DSA's National Convention. Some recordings of meetings, on audio and videocassettes, also are included.
  - National Executive Committee Meeting, June 2-3, 1984 (Box 155, Audiocassette 105_0102-105_0103, 105_0111, Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0238-105_0240)
  - National Board Meeting, Los Angeles, November 10, 1988 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0241)
  - DSA National Board Outreach Meeting with Conn, Meyerson, Gallanter, Barbara Ehrenreich, and Michael Harrington, 1988 (Box 159, Vhs 105_0163)
  - National Board Leadership School, June 12, 1992 (Box 164, Audiocassette 105_0242-105_0243)